<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../ODD/out/tei_brecon.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../ODD/BreconSchematron1.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?> 

<!-- this would be the more boilerplate declarations if I weren't using my own ODD and Schematron:
  <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?%>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
-->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letters Patent of Henry VIII Establishing Christ College and Church, Brecon,
                    Wales</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="W">Willis, Browne. _An History of the Mitred Parliamentary Abbies,
                        and Conventual Cathedral Churches_, vol. II (London, 1719), pp.
                        303-309. </bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="S"> Stevens, John. _The History of the antient abbeys,
                        monasteries, hospitals, cathedral and collegiate churches. Being two
                        additional volumes to Sir William Dugdale's Monasticon Anglicanum_ (London,
                        1722-1723), vol. II, Appendix pp. 372-374 (doc. 464).</bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="J"> Jones, Theophilus. _A History of the County of Brecknock_ 
                        (Brecknock, 1809; 2nd edn., 1898), Vol. II, Appendix (unpaginated: doc. IX).</bibl>

                    <msDesc xml:id="C">
                        <!-- This is witness C -->
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <country>United Kingdom</country>
                            <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                            <repository>St John's College</repository>
                            <idno>MS. H.12</idno>
                            <altIdentifier type="SC">
                                <!-- what does this type SC mean? -->
                                <idno>279</idno>
                            </altIdentifier>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                            <msItem n="1" class="statutes" defective="true">
                                <locus from="1" to="254">pp. 1-254</locus> 
                                <title type="supplied">Statutes of St Davids Cathedral</title>
                                <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>
                                <incipit>Hæc sunt Acta et Statuta in Ecclesia Meneven'</incipit>
                                <explicit>ταῦτα μέν δὴ ταῦτα</explicit>
                                <!--whc 9 June 2022: If Greek in explicit here isn't showing up properly in oXygen, change font to Palatino Linotype. Options- preferences- font. I turned that font back off because it's harder on the eyes on 
                                    a computer screen even if it's more aesthetically pleasing. -->
                            </msItem>   
                            <msItem n="2" class="Letters Patent" defective="false">
                                <locus from="255" to="265">pp. 255-265</locus>
                                <note place="top margin" hand="Thomas Baker">Subsequentes Literæ Patentes aliunde desumuntur, non occurrunt in Libro Statutorum Meneven.</note>
                                <title type="supplied">Brecon Charter</title>
                                <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>
                                <incipit>Henricus Octavus</incipit>
                                <explicit>Per Breve de Privato Sigillo et de Dat' prædict' &amp; c./</explicit>
                            </msItem>
                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                            <objectDesc form="codex">
                                <supportDesc material="chart"><!-- "chart" is used for paper, "perg" for parchment -->
                                <support>
                                    <num type="front-flyleaf" value="3"/>
                                    <num type="book-block" value="133"/>
                                    <num type="end-flyleaf" value="11"/>
                                    <dimensions type="leaf">
                                        <height unit="mm" quantity="365"/>
                                        <width unit="mm" quantity="235"/>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <dimensions type="cover">
                                        <height unit="mm" quantity="377"/>
                                        <width unit="mm" quantity="250"/>
                                    </dimensions>
                                </support>
                                <foliation>Flyleaves and endleaves not foliated or paginated; main text block paginated in hand roughly contemporary with text</foliation>
                                <collation>(not determined)</collation>    
                                    <condition>Excellent condition overall, except that iron-gall ink has burned its way into the paper where large, broad-stroked letters are used at the
                                    beginning of sections of the text; visible sometimes as show-through to other side of folio and/or offset on facing folio</condition>
                                </supportDesc>
                                <layoutDesc>
                                    <layout columns="1" ruledLines="41">
                                    <dimensions type="written">
                                        <height unit="mm" quantity="317"/>
                                        <width unit="mm" quantity="172"/> 
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <catchwords>Plain catchwords appear at the bottom right corner of almost every page, either inserted within the writing frame below
                                    the last line or added just below the writing frame in the bottom margin.</catchwords>
                                    <signatures>No obvious quire signature marks.</signatures>
                                    <secFol>Magister Robertus de Mora</secFol>
                                    </layout>
                                    </layoutDesc>
                            </objectDesc>
                            <handDesc><handNote>Main text written in one clear hand throughout; some notes in distinctive hand of Thomas Baker</handNote></handDesc>
                            <scriptDesc><p><!--different scripts, general type: describe--></p></scriptDesc>
                            <decoDesc><decoNote>One or more initial word(s) of each document written in broad-stroked, larger (approx. two lines) imitation Gothic quadrata hand; 
                                each subsection of the text begins with one word in a medium-sized imitation Gothic quadrata hand, larger than main text hand but
                                written so as to extend above and below writing lines and thus not occupy a two-line space.</decoNote></decoDesc>
                            <additions><p>There are marginal annotations on most pages.</p></additions>
                            <bindingDesc><p>Brown soft leather cover, but red soft leather spine; pencil note
                                inside back cover reads "Re-backed &amp; repaired by J. P. Gray May
                                1972 for £7.50." Binding is tight enough that it can be difficult to read marginalia in gutter margin.</p></bindingDesc>
                        </physDesc>
                        <history>
                            <provenance>
                                <p>Given to St John's College by Bishop Thomas Watson of St Davids (bishop
                                    1687-1699), a benefactor of the College (Yardley, _Menevia
                                    Sacra_ pp. 118-19, 384). Written <origDate>before 1717, when
                                        Watson died, and probably before 1699, when he was deprived
                                        of his bishopric, as it may have been difficult for him to
                                        acquire it thereafter.</origDate> Remains in Old Library at
                                    St Johns College. Consulted by Yardley in compiling _Menevia
                                    Sacra_ (1739-1769); page numbers align with those given in his
                                    digest of the statutes (National Library of Wales,
                                    SDCh/B/31).</p>
                            </provenance>
                        </history>
                    </msDesc>

                    <msDesc xml:id="D">
                        <!-- This is witness D -->
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                            <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                            <idno>SDCh/B/23</idno>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                            <msItem>
                                <title>Statutes of St Davids</title>
                                <title>Brecon Charter</title>
                                <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>
                            </msItem>

                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                            <p>
                                <material>Paper</material>: ff. ii + 181 pp + ff?. Pages 26.5 cm x
                                41 cm; writing area 18.4 cm x 36.5 cm. Brown leather cover. Written
                                in one clear hand throughout, similar but not identical to main hand
                                of C, with annotations in one or more other hands.</p>
                        </physDesc>
                        <history>
                            <provenance>
                                <p>Note in pen on f. ii r: "It appearing by an Attestation wrote
                                    over against the first Page of the Statute-Book of this
                                    Cathedral Church [now N.L.W., SDCh/B/22] that in the year 1719
                                    the said Statute-Book was collated by the late Bishop Ottley
                                    &amp; the late Mr. Chantor Davies with a much more ancient
                                    manuscript of the said Statutes [now British Library, Harley MS
                                    6280], which was attested A[nn]o 1588 by Bishop Middleton,
                                    Chantor Huett &amp; c., &amp; which said ancient Copy has ever
                                    since been unfortunately missing (which is greatly lamented) or
                                    at least was never seen by any of the present members of the
                                    Chapter; -Richard Davies Archdeacon of St. Davids &amp; one of
                                    the Canons Residentiary of this Church made many Enquiries with
                                    various Persons and in various places, in order to the
                                    recovering, if possible, the said ancient manuscript: and
                                    particularly haveing procured diligent search to be made for
                                    that purpose among the Books and Papers of the said late Mr.
                                    Chantor Davies, altho' the Book in question could not, upon such
                                    serch, be found, yet the present manuscript (containing not only
                                    the St. Davids Statutes, but also the Patent of King Henry the
                                    Eighth for founding Christ's College in Brecon) being met with
                                    among the said Books, was, at the Request of the said
                                    Archdeacon, generously made a Present of to the Chantor and
                                    Chapter of St. Davids by the Reverend Mr. Richard Davies Master
                                    of Arts, Golden Prebendary of this Church [NB he held the preb.
                                    of Mathrey, alias the Golden Prebend, form 1723 to his d. in May
                                    1745], on order to be laid up in the Chapter-Chest of this
                                    Cathedral, where it is accordingly deposited this 25th day of
                                    July in the Year one thousand seven hundred and forty eight by
                                    me Richard Davies Archdeacon of St. Davids." [pencil note
                                    below:] "Qu. whether this is in the British Museum."
                                        <origDate>Before 14 Dec. 1732</origDate>, when Precentor
                                    (Chantor) John Davies died. Remains in the legal ownership of
                                    the Dean and Chapter of St Davids; placed on deposit at National
                                    Library of Wales.</p>
                            </provenance>
                        </history>
                    </msDesc>


                    <msDesc xml:id="I">
                        <!--  WHC October 24 2019: This is witness I. -->
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                            <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                            <idno>SDCh/B/25</idno>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                            <msItem>
                                <title>Statutes of St Davids</title>
                                <title>Brecon Charter</title>
                                <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>
                            </msItem>

                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                            <p>
                                <material>Paper</material>: ff. vi + pp. 278 + ff. xliv (blank).
                                Pages 23 x 36 cm; writing frame 16.4 x 29.6cm. Not ruled. Grey
                                leather cover, apparently by NLW. Written in one clear hand
                                throughout.</p>
                        </physDesc>
                        <history>
                            <provenance>
                                <p>Origin unknown. This is the principal copy consulted by Edward
                                    Yardley in compiling _Menevia Sacra_. This can be determined by
                                    the fact that the page numbers he supplies in his marginal
                                    notations (rendered as footnotes in the publication by editor
                                    Francis Green) align with the page numbers in this manuscript.
                                    Yardley's partial transcript of the Brecon charter on p. 415 of
                                    _Menevia Sacra_ references "Ex libro Episcopi Menev., Stat.
                                    Menev., p. 269. Compare this with ye same Charter printed in B.
                                    Willis, Abb. Vol. ii, p. 304." The document in question begins
                                    on p. 269 in this manuscript. More fully, Yardley's digest of
                                    the statutes (National Library of Wales, MS SDCh/B/31, not
                                    published by Green) has page references throughout, which again
                                    align with the page numbers in this manuscript. This is our only
                                    indication of this manuscript's date. Yardley began his
                                    researches in 1739 and appears to have completed the main
                                    substance of _Menevia Sacra_ around the mid-1740s, though he
                                    continued to add new members to his lists of canons and
                                    dignitaries until the early 1760s (_Menevia Sacra_, p. iv;
                                    National Library of Wales, MS. SDCh/B/30). It is likely that he
                                    was alredy using this manuscript in the 1740s; the latest
                                    possible terminus ante quem is 1769, the year in which Yardley
                                    died. <origDate>Probably before 1746.</origDate>, </p>
                            </provenance>
                        </history>
                    </msDesc>


                    <msDesc xml:id="O">
                        <!--  WHC October 24 2019: This is witness O. Need to check published diary/letters of Humphrey Wanley, but I think number 1249 suggests Harley had it before extant diary begins, and 6280 suggests Harley acquired it much later. -->
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <settlement>London</settlement>
                            <repository>British Library</repository>
                            <idno>Harley MS 1249</idno>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                            <msItem>
                                <title>Statutes of St Davids</title>
                                <title>Brecon Charter</title>
                                <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>
                            </msItem>

                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                            <p>
                                <material>Paper</material>: pp/ff??. Cover 25cm x 38 cm; pages about
                                23.5 x 36.5; writing frame 16.5 x 33. Not ruled. Red cover, buckram
                                with leather spine and corners. Written in one clear hand
                                throughout.</p>
                        </physDesc>
                        <history>
                            <provenance>
                                <p>Origin unknown. Two letters are pasted in among foreleaves. One
                                    from Bishop Adam Ottley (bishop of St Davids 1713-23) mentions
                                    borrowing a copy of the Statutes from Robert Harley, 1st Earl of
                                    Oxford, though this may in fact refer to the MS that is now
                                    Harley 6280, which Ottley used to check National Library of
                                    Wales, MS SDCh/B/22 in 1719. The other is from his successor,
                                    Richard Smallbrook (bishop of St Davids 1724-1731) in 1729,
                                    promising to return to Edward Harley, 2nd Earl of Oxford, a copy
                                    of the statutes (either Harley 6280 or this present volume)
                                    which he had borrowed to use in a suit in the Court of Arches to
                                    oblige canons of St Davids to residence. Harley 6280 was in the
                                    hands of Thomas Baker at Cambridge at an unknown date between
                                    1719 and his death in 1740 (Bodleian Library, Willis MS. 38 f.
                                    531r-v), and may not have entered Harley's collection yet. It may be that Harley 1249 was thus the only copy
                                    Harley had to lend to Smallbrook at this time. Moreover, Smallbrook would have recognized that Harley 6280 properly belonged to the cathedral chapter, while Harley 1249 bears no marks that it belonged to anyone other than Harley; thanks for a loan with a promise to return a book would make sense if the book was 1249 but not 6280.
                                        <origDate>Probably before 1729.</origDate>, </p>
                            </provenance>
                        </history>
                    </msDesc>

                    <msDesc xml:id="R">
                        <!--  WHC October 24 2019: This is witness R. -->
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <settlement>London</settlement>
                            <repository>The National Archives</repository>
                            <idno>C 66/709</idno>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                            <msItem>
                                <title>Chancery Patent Roll, 33 Henry VIII Part 9</title>
                                <title>Brecon Charter</title>
                                <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>
                            </msItem>

                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                            <p>
                                <material>Parchment</material> roll consisting of stitched
                                membranes. Written in abbreviated Latin in the standard Chancery
                                hand used in the Patent Rolls.</p>
                        </physDesc>
                        <history>
                            <provenance>
                                <p>Produced by Chancery, the office that issued and enrolled Letters Patent (for details of the process, see https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015008927983&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1). The 'original' against which it was checked (see note at end of text) was not the Letter Patent that had been issued, but rather the Warrant in Chancery, the authorised draft from which the Letter itself was prepared. This may survive in The National Archives in the file C 82/776, which contains the surviving Warrants in Chancery for January of 32 Henry VIII (1541).The Patent Rolls were initially stored in the Rolls Chapel in the
                                    Tower of London; moved to the new Public Record Office building
                                    in Chancery Lane in the 1850s and thence to the second Public
                                    Record Office building in Kew in the 1990s. The Public Record
                                    Office became The National Archives in 2003. <origDate>January
                                        32 Henry VIII: 1540 (Old Style) / 1541 (New
                                        Style)</origDate>, according to date on document, though enrolled among documents of 33 Henry VIII.</p>
                            </provenance>
                        </history>
                    </msDesc>
                    
                    <msDesc xml:id="Z">
                        <!--  WHC June 7 2022: This is witness Z. -->
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <settlement>London</settlement>
                            <repository>The National Archives</repository>
                            <idno>C 82/776</idno>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                            <msItem>
                                <title>Warrants for the Great Seal, January, 32 Henry VIII (1541 N.S.)</title>
                                <title>Brecon Charter</title>
                                <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>
                            </msItem>
                            
                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                            <p>
                                <material>Parchment</material>; bundle of several dozen membranes, joined by tag at upper left corner, not individually catalogued. The document of interest
                                is the second-last membrane in the bundle. Badly soiled, wrinkled, and abraded, especially in upper left corner near where tag joins the membranes together 
                                and thus leads to most abrasion with the dorse of the previous document; that area is legible only under ultraviolet light. Written in abbreviated Latin in a 
                                standard cursive Chancery hand.</p>
                        </physDesc>
                        <history>
                            <provenance>
                                <p>Produced by Chancery, the office that issued and enrolled Letters Patent 
                                    (for details of the process, see https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015008927983&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1). 
                                    The 'original' against which it was checked (see note at end of text) was not the Letter Patent that had been issued, 
                                    but rather the Warrant in Chancery, the authorised draft from which the Letter itself was prepared. 
                                    This may survive in The National Archives in the file C 82/776, which contains the surviving Warrants in Chancery for 
                                    January of 32 Henry VIII (1541). Initially stored in the Rolls Chapel in the
                                    Tower of London; moved to the new Public Record Office building
                                    in Chancery Lane in the 1850s and thence to the second Public
                                    Record Office building in Kew in the 1990s. The Public Record
                                    Office became The National Archives in 2003. <origDate>January,
                                        32 Henry VIII: 1540 (Old Style) / 1541 (New
                                        Style).</origDate></p>
                            </provenance>
                        </history>
                    </msDesc>
                    
                    <msDesc xml:id="Y">
                        <!--  WHC June 7 2022: This is witness Y. -->
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <settlement>London</settlement>
                            <repository>The National Archives</repository>
                            <idno>PSO 2/5</idno>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                            <msItem>
                                <title>Privy Seal Warrants, 32 Henry VIII</title>
                                <title>Brecon Charter</title>
                                <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>
                            </msItem>
                            
                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                            <p>
                                <material>Parchment</material>; bundle of several dozen membranes, joined by tag at upper left corner, not individually catalogued. Written in abbreviated Latin in a 
                                standard cursive Chancery hand.</p>
                        </physDesc>
                        <history>
                            <provenance>
                                <p>Warrant under signet, sent to Privy Seal Office, to prepare Warrant in Chancery (now C 82/776, and our Witness Z) 
                                    (for details of the process, see https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015008927983&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1). 
                                    This was the earliest draft stage of the process.
                                    <!-- WHC 7 June 2022: Need to check if provenance/custody of PSO docs is same as Chancery docs described here: -->
                                    The Patent Rolls were initially stored in the Rolls Chapel in the
                                    Tower of London; moved to the new Public Record Office building
                                    in Chancery Lane in the 1850s and thence to the second Public
                                    Record Office building in Kew in the 1990s. The Public Record
                                    Office became The National Archives in 2003. <origDate>January,
                                        33 Henry VIII: 1540 (Old Stye) / 1541 (New
                                        Style).</origDate></p>
                            </provenance>
                        </history>
                    </msDesc>
                    
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <ab>
                <!-- This is an empty node in the msDesc-only document holding the place of the text in the main document. -->
            </ab>
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>

